Yoonsu Kim

Ph.D. Student | HCI Researcher

☑ yoonsu16@kaist.ac.kr | kysoo816@gmail.com 🏠 https://yoonsu0816.github.io/

Research Interests

My research interests include around **Human-Computer Interaction**, **Human-Centered AI**, and **Human-AI** collaboration.

I am passionate about developing new interactions and systems that help people better utilize AI technology and understand the difficulties in using or trying to use it.

Education

KAIST

Ph.D. in School of Computing

Advisor: <u>Juho Kim</u>

KAIST

M.S. in AI (Specialization: Human-AI Interaction)

Advisor: Juho Kim

POSTECH

B.S. in Computer Science and Engineering

Magna cum laude

Feb 2024 - Present

Daejeon, Republic of Korea

Feb 2022 - Feb 2024

Daejeon, Republic of Korea

Feb 2017 - Feb 2022

Pohang, Republic of Korea

Publications

Conferences and Journal Papers

[C1] Understanding Users' Dissatisfaction with ChatGPT Responses: Types, Resolving Tactics, and the Effect of Knowledge Level

Yoonsu Kim, Jueon Lee, Seoyoung Kim, Jaehyuk Park, Juho Kim *IUI 2024*

[C2] AI-to-Human Actuation: AI Proactively Induces Humans towards Favorable Sensing Conditions

Sungjae Cho, **Yoonsu Kim**, Jaewoong Jang, Inseok Hwang *IMWUT 2023*

Posters, Demos, and Workshop Papers

[D1] LLM-as-a-tutor in EFL Writing Education: Focusing on Evaluation of Student-LLM Interaction

Jieun Han, Haneul Yoo, Junho Myung, Minsun Kim, Hyunseung Lim, **Yoonsu Kim**, Tak Yeon Lee, Hwajung Hong, Juho Kim, So-Yeon Ahn, Alice Oh

EMNLP 2024 Workshop on Customizable NLP (CustomNLP4U).

Last updated: Nov 2, 2024

[D2] LLM-Driven Learning Analytics Dashboard for Teachers in EFL Writing Education

Minsun Kim, Junho Myung, Seon Gyeom Kim, Yoosang Yoon, Hyunseung Lim, Yoonsu Kim, Hwajung Hong, Alice Oh, Juho Kim, So-Yeon Ahn, and Tak Yeon Lee EMNLP 2024 Workshop on Customizable NLP (CustomNLP4U).

[D3] Using Large Language Models to Diagnose Math Problem-Solving Skills at Scale

Hyoungwook Jin*, Yoonsu Kim*, Yeon Su Park, Bekzat Tilekbay, Jinho Son, Juho Kim (* Corresponding authors) L@S 2024 WIP

[D4] Beyond Prompts: Learning from Human Communication for Enhanced AI Intent Alignment Yoonsu Kim, Kihoon Son, Seoyoung Kim, Juho Kim

CHI 2024 Workshop on Getting Back Together: HCI and Human Factors Joining Forces to Meet the AI Interaction Challenge

[D5] RECIPE: How to Integrate ChatGPT into EFL Writing Education

Jieun Han, Haneul Yoo, Yoonsu Kim, Junho Myung, Minsun Kim, Hyunseung Lim, Juho Kim, Tak Yeon Lee, Hwajung Hong, So-Yeon Ahn, Alice Oh L@S 2023 WIP

[D6] Towards Understanding the Challenges and Remedies in AI Application Development

Dae Hyun Kim*, Yoonsu Kim*, Hyungyu Shin, Jinho Son, Juho Kim (* Corresponding authors) KCC 2023

[D7] Demonstrating AHA: Boosting Unmodified AI's Robustness by Proactively Inducing **Favorable Human Sensing Conditions**

Sungjae Cho, Jaewoong Jang, Yoonsu Kim, Inseok Hwang UbiComp/ISWC '23 Adjunct

Experiences

HIS Lab (Human-Centered Intelligent System Lab in POSTECH)

Jun 2021 - Feb 2022

Research Intern

Human-Computer Interaction, Human-AI Interaction, Embedded AI System

Pohang, Republic of Korea

NAVER Connect Foundation

Manager of boostcamp

Web & Mobile, AI Software Education

Feb 2020 - Feb 2021

Seoul, Republic of Korea

Neuromeka

Software Development Intern Android application development for robot manipulation and robot database management

Jun 2019 - Aug 2019 Pohang, Republic of Korea

Samsung Electronics Co.

Research Intern Department of Visual Display, AI • Big Data Lab

Jan 2019 - Feb 2019 Suwon, Republic of Korea

SK Telecom

Software Development Intern Department of Service Platform

Jun 2018 - Aug 2018 Seoul, Republic of Korea

AI Technology Unit, Knowledge and Technology Cell

Last updated: Nov 2, 2024

Scholarship

National Scholarship (Science and Engineering) 2017 - 2023

Global Leadership Program Mar 2018 - Feb 2020

Samsung Dream Class Scholarship Jan 2018 ~ Feb 2018

Leadership & Service

Leadership

HCI@KAIST Committee
Student Committee
Mar 2024 - Present

KAIST-Google exploreCSR

Student Organizer Mar 2023 - Aug 2024

POSTECH Student Council
Director of Welfare Department
Feb 2019 - Feb 2021

POSTECH Library Council
President, Vice President

Mar 2017 - Aug 2019

POSTECH Reader's Club 6
(Awarded by Excellent Mentee)

POSTECH Reader's Club 5

Feb 2019 - Dec 2018

Teaching

POSTECH Programming and Problem Solving (CSED101)
Teaching Mentor

Feb 2021 - Dec 2021

Volunteering

Volunteer Activities

KOICA WFK Korean Medicine Volunteer Group Overseas Medical

Volunteer Activities

Krong Battambang,
Cambodia

KOICA WFK Korean Medicine Volunteer Group Overseas Medical

Aug 2019

Toshken, Uzbekistan